Let's do it live on a Tuesday edition of
the program. Happy St. Patrick's Day.
>> Although looking out there, it doesn't
quite feel Well, maybe it does. Just
kind of the way it goes here. Maybe it
does. Merely Bo, the great Z and
luminaries right out of the gate.
>> Yes.
>> New defensive coordinator Mike Rutenberg
in studio with us. Mike, good to see
you, man.
>> Great to see you guys.
>> How's it been?
>> It's been awesome. It's been awesome. It
uh great town here. Uh I've gotten
around a little bit. Really, really cool
people. It's a football town. Great
building, man. Uh, getting to know some
of the people in the building, the
coaches, Coach Monk, and some of the
players that I've been around. It's It's
really been awesome. It's been fun every
day.
>> What What is it like when you you get
this nod, the ultimate nod, defensive
coordinator, you get this that you got
familiar guys on the staff that you've
known through various places. Your story
is incredible how you got to this point.
Um, and I'm sure you're chomping at the
bit to get going and you're jumping on a
treadmill that's moving. How have you
managed all this professionally and
personally over the last month? for
sure. Um, well, I appreciate you saying
that. My story is just like everybody
else's story. You got a story, you got a
story. Uh, all the coaches and the
players have a story, and that's what's
most important. Um, the way I've managed
it is just meet as many people as I can,
including you guys. Start to build the
relationships. I understand part of
relationships is earning trust and
building trust. And that's a two-way
street. And whether it's Coach Monkin,
uh, Andrew, the organization, ownership,
the people in the building, the players,
it's all about the relationships. I I
said it earlier, learning each other's
why, touching each other's heart, sh
learning your story, sharing my story,
and eventually we just build an awesome
connection that becomes unbreakable,
man.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. I love it. Just as you said,
>> I want to So, we've we've got to talk a
few times with Hall, but like he's just
Yeah. Go ahead. Say what you're going to
say.
>> I just say Tarv.
>> Well, I mean, like it's the energy,
right?
>> So, we are very close with Jason Tarv on
the show and and a lot of the guys
obviously on that defensive staff, those
guys have all been here for a little
while, but Tarv's like our guy. We love
>> Tarv.
>> And when you know, going through the
process and when he we found out Rudy,
you were going to be the new defensive
coordinator and we were like, "All
right, well, you know, what do you
think?" And he's like, "You guys are
going to love him." He's like, "He's a
lot like me." And I was like, "Yeah, and
you're just a younger younger tarf,
which we absolutely love. guys who love
ball, great energy, but are real people
people as well for sure. You know, as
you said, you care about those
connections. We heard Quincy Williams,
you talked about it in yours. We've
heard Quincy talk about it when I got a
chance to interview him talk about the
relationship you guys started down in
Jacksonville and carried through through
New York. But
>> that's what is I think what's cool about
this league is, you know, you go
through, we were just kind of bsing
before we were talking about that year
you're with the NerS and you listed off
a ton of people staff that I know
because they were here, a lot of them in
2014 or 2015 even after that. um with
those guys, but just it's that
connective tissue in the league. And for
you to come in, you know, first time DC,
you got a lot of these guys here and to
already have formed the bonds you have
from just the guys that we talked to, I
think is really cool. And I love that
that's what's
>> so important to you because without
people, this is people. This is the
game's played by people. What else is
there?
>> It's all It's a people business. I just
think it's very cool the way you've come
in like that and just the energy you
bring. We like energy. Energy is Yeah.
No doubt. You can tell.
>> Me, too.
>> What was your approach you took? Um, and
and you I'm sure when you're you're
coming up and you're going on this path
to get to a point of a defensive
coordinator and uh the position that
you're in now, what was kind of in your
head as you walked into the building
talking to guys who had been here and
you've had familiarity with some of them
certainly, but just in terms of what
what did you want your staff to be all
about and what were some of those early
messages you you you kind of passed
along to the guys?
>> I'm going to sound repetitive. It's just
cuz and I I don't like the word I and
we're going to try not to use that cuz
it's us and we but
>> um for me the first thing was just
starting those relationships, learning
the people, learning their why, learning
what's important to them. Is it family?
Is it hobbies? Is it football? And then
finding out how I can share my stories
and I can hear their stories and we
start to build that bond. So before any
messaging, before any heart, mind, fist,
as you're going to hear a lot, was just
learning each other, learning what's
been done here and why they've been so
successful here. Learning where can we
make it ours.
>> All right. And then the messaging of
what's most important. You're going to
hear me say this all the time. It's just
it's in my DNA. It's going to be style
over scheme. We are going to attack. We
are going to play fast. We're going to
play hard. We're going to play smart.
We're going to play violent. That's
heartmind fist right there. And then the
ball is going to be our oxygen. We are
going after the ball. Our heart is going
to be our connection to each other and
the way we celebrate. Our mind is our
deliberate approach and how smart we
play. We're problem solvers here. And
the fist, I don't know if this is the
appropriate time to talk about the fist,
but you guys know.
>> I think it speaks for itself.
>> Yeah. Perfect.
>> There's two right there on the wall.
>> No doubt. That's fist right there. And
that's that dark room. And that starts
with the engine up front.
>> And then the ball is oxygen. And without
oxygen, we all know you die. That's the
truth. Did you have a connection with
with Todd really from I guess in in
Jacksonville? Did you guys cross pass or
not? Not not even there.
>> We did not.
>> So how did this like how did that you
get a call I imagine that's like hey
>> you want to come coach a defense with
Miles Garrett on it and you're like
>> yes
>> yeah in fact I do as a matter of fact
and you also have the other part that
you were coming from Atlanta which has a
little tie to us right now as our former
head coach was down there. So kind of
just walk us through how this all came
to be because
>> just walk us through it.
>> Sure. I let me say this. I'm so
appreciative to Todd, uh, to Andrew
Barry, to to the HLMS, and to the
organization for giving me this
opportunity. I'm not going to dive super
deep into all the things that go into
it, but the interview process was
incredible. Yeah. Um, through the
interview process, getting to know Todd,
getting to know Andrew, and then getting
to know the ownership group and Mr.
Hasslam was an incredible process of
learning, and it became very clear to me
that this is a place I want to be, not
only because of Todd AB, and Mr. Mr.
Hasslam in the organization, but in
doing the research, the players that are
here. Yeah. At at every level of defense
and then the coaching staff that was
already here, it just became something
that I was extremely interested in and
feel very fortunate to have the
opportunity and thankful to all those
people.
>> Were you guys kind of surprised like
because you know to it this is often a
business where it's like I know you and
for example you work with Salah, Salah
goes to the Jets. Hey, I want to bring
you with me. You get the opportunity to
go to the Jets and do that.
>> Yeah. And this is a case where you guys
didn't have that background, but I'm
sure there was connective tissue people
he knew that you knew and vice versa in
the conversations. But were you kind of
surprised and then obviously very happy
and were thrilled you're sitting here?
>> Well, thank you. I'm thrilled too.
Pleasantly surprised for sure. And like
you mentioned the connective tissue that
goes back to for me a lot of the people
who are the reason I'm here both players
and coaches. You mentioned Robert Salah.
He's always supported me in my career,
whether we're at Jacksonville, bringing
me in the linebacker room and teaching
me how to prepare players. Yeah. Become,
you know, going to the New York Jets and
building that defense along with Jeff
Olrich, who I credit personally for
teaching me how to lead through
relationships, who got me to Raheem
Morris, who is the ultimate ultimate
dealer in solutions. There are no
problems. We deal in solutions. And all
those guys along with a lot of other
people, Gus Bradley teaching me the
precision in league. These are names,
guys, that I'm not dropping. These are
names that are so important to me
because they helped me become who I am
today. The players who have taught me to
coach the way I am. Sure.
>> Going back to Paul Lesnney taught me
what a player needs.
>> Stud
linebackers down there.
>> Stud. Don't teach me how to take on a
guard. Teach me when a guard's pulling.
Got you, Puzz. No problem.
>> Taught me about formation and
anticipation and responding. And I could
continue to go through those players.
because we got one here in Quincy
Williams who could not be more excited
about and Jesse Bates and Xavier Watts
and again these are players and coaches
who came before who helped me get this
opportunity. beyond appreciative of all
those people.
>> This all comes so fast, I have to
assume. I mean, you mentioned no
previous relationship with Todd.
Obviously, you knew some guys around
here. We knew Todd from 19. Yeah.
>> And it's so interesting. And listen,
obviously your press conferences and we
know Todd a little bit.
>> If you were to say these guys didn't
previously know each other, I would have
said you're nuts because just that your
approaches are so similar. Uh the
directness that he has, you're very
direct. You ask a question, you get an
answer. How how quickly in your
conversations with Todd were you like,
"Oh, I can do that. This will be a fit."
>> So, full disclosure, we had met before.
Okay. Okay. And and you know, when you
meet Coach Monk, you see the directness,
and that's something that you appreciate
so much. That's what you want. But you
see the care as well. You see the
commitment to listening and conversation
and getting his full attention. That's a
tribute to him. We started the process
and I immediately felt like this is a
guy I want to be around.
>> This is a guy who I want to coach
football with. This is a guy who I want
to talk to. This is a guy I want to do
really hard things with and celebrate
when we have success together. And if it
doesn't go well at times, I know this is
a guy who when we're get we're together,
we're going to lock arms and fight our
butts off to get it right. And I started
to see that through the process. And
then naturally, you do research, right,
as different opportunities come. and all
the research is like this is a guy you
want to be around. This is a guy who you
want to do hard stuff with. It just kept
coming back and I'm like well let's just
go do it then.
>> Absolutely.
>> That's great.
>> You come into a situation where the
defense here has been very good and it
plays a particular style and you have
experience. You know you understand this
style. You also have some other
backgrounds and styles that you've
understood on the back end especially in
the past game. How do you come in and
want to kind of put your imprint on it
but also say as you said we're about the
results the results have been like these
guys are pretty good in this and a lot
of them kind of fit that scheme. How do
you balance that as you come in because
this is your first time as defensive
coordinator. This is going to be the
Rudy defense and it's everybody's
defense but you're at the top of it.
>> I was about to I got you. I got you. I
got you. I got you. You saw my body. Not
my first rodeo. Yeah. Right. How do you
go about thinking about how you want to
attack that knowing you're going to
have, you know, OTAAS, you got training
camp and that plan to to get it to where
it is the 2026 runs? Because evolution
is a fact of life and it's a fact of the
NFL. If you're not evolving, you're
getting past.
>> No doubt. Um, we have like two hours,
but I'll give you long as long as you
want. We can go 90 and then we'll just
throw all commercial D. We'll all be out
of here early because I Yeah, there we
go.
>> Well, first things first and and we
joked about this is our defense. It's
our defense. It's the players defense.
It's the coaches defense. It's the
Cleveland Browns defense. Yep. And our
whole goal is to play championship
defense. There's no magic scheme that
does that. There's a mentality and a
style that does that. And we're going to
continue to build on the style that's in
place here. Amazing respect for what's
been done here. But now, how can we make
it ours? How can we keep it going and
get that much more? How can we play that
much harder, that much smarter, that
much more violent? How can we go after
the ball that much more? Everybody's got
every front in coverage in the NFL.
Everybody's got it in college. The
secret sauce is our play style and it's
always going to be that style over
scheme. We're going to talk about it.
It's going to start with our attacking
mentality up front. It's never going to
change. That's going to be our engine.
And we go as our engine goes. And to me,
that's the secret sauce of playing great
defense. That's how we're going to make
it ours. Of course, we're going to
install scheme. Of course, we're going
to do different things that we think
will help our players to put them in the
best position to play championship
defense, but it's always going to start
with the heart mind fist and going after
the ball.
>> One thing I want to ask you about
because you're going to get to call the
plays now. Is that something that you
would when you were in your previous
roles, you'd be thinking about, oh man,
I would do this here or I would do that.
And you're on the headsets and I'm sure
in communicating with whether it's Salo,
whoever you're doing down Old Brook down
there in Atlanta.
Now that you get to do that, that's
something everybody loves to do.
Everybody's played Madden can relate to
that, right? You can you pick the plays.
I think
>> Long time since I played Madden.
>> Well, you're playing real, you got real
Madden happening on the field. You're
doing the real life stuff that they
create the game about. But is that
something you're excited about and the
chess match of it? And, you know, I
think it's got to be fun for you having
a guy like, you know, Dom Capers
obviously who's here now who's head
coach and he's done it at at a high
level, but also then Todd to be like,
"All right, this situation, what would
you be thinking? What would you be
thinking?" I'm thinking what, you know,
goes back to the Princess Bride kind of
how do you figure out which cup you can
ultimately drink? But is that something
you're really excited about that in-game
chess match that now you're you're the
one moving the pieces? You're making
those calls.
>> I'm I'm excited about this whole process
because I'm excited to watch our
players. Yeah.
>> I can't wait to watch our style come to
life. In the end, calling the play is
doing our best to put our players in the
best su in the best position to win by
what we've prepared for. But more
important than that is are we building
our style, our DNA, playing hard,
playing violent, playing attacking,
playing grimy. To answer your question,
as I was going through the process of my
career and my journey, just like every
other coach's process and journey, for
me,
>> I just tried to be where my feet were at
all times. I really did try and embrace
and own the moments that I was in and
naturally learn what was going on around
me because I just wanted to embrace
those moments and get the most I could
out of those moments. And then in the
opportunities that I did to have call
plays, I acknowledge it wasn't in a
regular season game. I tried to take
what I had learned and what had kind of
become part of me and naturally call the
plays that I thought would put the
players in the best position to succeed.
And then in the end, as you're calling
plays, you're watching, are we playing
hard? Are we playing fast? Are we
playing smart? ARE WE PLAYING VI? ARE WE
SHOWCASING OUR style to make ourselves
the organization proud to play
championship defense?
>> You said there um all of our journeys
are the same. Yours is a little
different.
>> Was when you get to this point, do you
look back 25 years and you think about
you're finishing up at Cornell. When did
it hit you that you were going to
attempt to go on this journey? And I say
attempt because there is no promises for
sure.
>> You know how this can go. At any point
you get with the wrong guy, you're done
and you're doing something else and
>> God knows what. But
>> the conversations you had then with
people who were important to you that
led you to this point when you look back
on that is it it's it's got it's an
unbelievable r it's it's a crazy path.
How did when you look back on that, how
do you reflect? Well, I appreciate you
saying that, but um and humbly every
coach, every business person, you guys
guys, we all have a story. It started
somewhere.
>> Yeah.
>> And we all had different paths and
different people who helped us along the
way. And as I reflect back on it,
>> I'm just super thankful to the people
that helped me along the way. And I'm
super thankful to the experiences that I
had. I can't sit there and tell you in
the moment I was like, "Oh, this is
definitely going to help me do this."
>> Yeah. But I'm super appreciative of the
process and I'm still on that process
and we're all still on that process and
hopefully we can just continue to own
each moment and continue to get better
in that process.
>> Was there ever though I'm sure there had
to be moments you're like is this going
to work? Like
>> do you know who
>> you have to have self-doubt?
>> Do you know who the first head coach?
>> I do know who the first coach he worked
for. But like so it's it's Joe Gibbs out
of the gate.
>> Well, it's Spurer. Steve, I was the
personnel assistant and credit to Vinnie
Sorado who gave me my first job.
>> To get deeper into your question,
>> when in eighth grade when I realized I
couldn't get the ball to second base as
the catcher and the guy was stealing
second base, I was like, "All right,
this isn't going to work. So, let let me
figure out where I can find success."
And I got this amazing opportunity from
Vinnie Serado who believed in me. And
fast forward to and I just didn't have a
ton of connection to coach Spur cuz I
was on the personnel side. Fast forward
to coach Gibbs who I saw first and
foremost the true definition of hard
work. So I joined him on the ride and
said let's just work and fight as hard
as we possibly can.
>> And no, I never thought what's going to
happen because you don't have time to
think about that. You embrace each
moment for that. That moment was just
hard work. I have no idea what my job
description was for Coach Gibbs. I love
you coach, but I don't think you do
either. But we just worked. just works
>> and we fought and if he needed it, we
got it done. That's it. And I was
fortunate to meet Dwayne Walker there
who at one time was a Cleveland Browns,
fortunate to meet Dale Lindseay there,
who played for the Cleveland Browns and
that brought me to a GA job at UCLA. And
like every other GA, you work and you
figure it out and eventually you meet
people and players who start to teach
you about football. Mhm.
>> And hopefully you're able to internalize
that information, to get creative with
that information, to get adaptive with
that information to figure out what you
think what works. And again, remember,
it's not the secret sauce of the scheme.
The scheme is important, but it's what
makes players tick, what makes players
go, what's our style, what do we look
like, what's the fan in the stands
leaving the game saying that Cleveland
BROWNS DEFENSE IS VIOLENT AS CAN BE.
>> All right. Almost used a curse word
there. I did. They're as violent as can
be.
>> Good job.
>> And thank you. And that's where for me,
Dwayne Walker brings me to New Mexico
State. I have the great fortune of being
a secondary coach at a young I gotta
figure it out. Let me tap into these
personalities. Let me figure out who
these young men are who to this day are
some of my favorite people in the human
beings, favorite human beings in the
world. Been invited to their weddings,
get pictures of their kids, and those
that's why you coach. And that just
continues. and you meet people and you
have experiences and you work as hard as
you freaking can and you get as creative
as you can and you try and collect as
much information as you can and figure
out what works by season by offseason by
season by offseason and that's exactly
what we're doing right now.
>> My kids are in the car right now and
they're 14 and 12. Boys, that's a lesson
in life.
>> Yeah.
>> Relationships, hard work, acumen, that
that whatever your profession is. That's
right. Yeah. That's that's it. That's
right.
>> That was that was a master class right
there, buddy.
>> It's awesome. And it's crazy your
connective tissue. One of the people who
still has a voice in this area was a
former defensive coordinator here, Greg
Williams. Son, Blake, when you got hired
and Greg Williams was the DC in 2004 on
that Washington.
>> Oh my gosh. Sure.
>> He was.
>> Greg and Blake, they were all like
Browns fans. You guys got a real one.
So, I mean, your connection to people
that have been here is kind of
>> staggering, honestly, when you go back
even to that 2003 staff. But, I think
that's cool. And that was, you know,
Greg had kind of that fire and, you
know, the get off and all those those
things, but it's fun to,
>> it's cool to hear the story and the
things that have shaped you. And it's
one of those things like it feels like
you take a little bit from everybody,
right? And you figure out, okay, I have
I really like this. I like this. I like
this. Here's who I am. How do I filter
that through me? So, it's genuine. And
then you get get to the point where you
are. Now, I mean, listen, Quincy
Williams, I got to sit down with him
for, I don't know, 10, 15 minutes. And
you can tell that he is a a an
interesting guy. He has a a very kind of
unique, I would say, outlook on the
world. But your ability to relate to a
Quincy Williams and then to relate to
somebody else who, for example, he's
going to be playing next to Carson
Swisser, I can tell you as somebody
who's sat spend time with both of them.
Football wise, probably very much same.
They want to be studs. Very different
personalities and approaches to the
world. But your ability to relate to
those people because you said it's a
people business. I just think it's very
cool like hearing you right now.
>> Y
>> you get us fired up.
>> There's a lot of tar in there which I
love. Like there's just love ball. Like
it's just ball and people. That's at the
end of the day.
>> That's it.
>> That's it. There's nothing better than
in my opinion the NFL locker room. All
the different people, the backgrounds,
the different outlooks, the different
upbringings, and can we all come
together to do some really hard stuff,
build relationships along the way, and
hoist a trophy together? What else is
there? It's the greatest art. There's
going to be ups. There's going to be
downs. We are going to thrive through
all of them because of our bond and our
relationships and to then hoist a trophy
and have success together. We'll
remember it not only for the success.
We'll remember those relationship. Can't
wait to be around Carson and Quincy and
then watch them jive together along with
everybody else on the defense. Yeah, cuz
it's all of us. There's 11 of us out
there and however many on the defense
and we're rolling together.
>> We don't know necessarily how the rules
are, but for you, has have you been able
to talk to any of the guys and kind of
introduce yourself and you know, I know
they'll be back here soon enough. Um,
but how's that kind of been coming in?
And you know, because the players are
probably like, "All right, this is the
similar, the same, but very very new and
and excited to meet you as well."
>> For sure. And it goes back to what we're
talking about. And again, I'm not going
to apologize for sounding like a broken
record because I just believe in it so
much.
>> It's starting the relationships. It's
meeting new people. It's hearing what's
important to them. hearing what makes
them go, what makes them tick on the
field, off the field, family, football,
and then once everybody's back and we're
within the rules of talking about
football, we'll head in that direction.
But I've had great conversations with
the guys of just meeting them and
hearing their voice and being able to
put I'm a big FaceTime guy, putting a
name with a face.
>> Got to see people
>> and just just learning who they are and
meeting them. That's been a great joy
along with everybody in the building,
which has been awesome.
>> Yeah. From a from a football team
defensive perspective, what are your
non-negotiables?
>> Heart, mind, fist, the ball is oxygen.
Build relationships. Done.
>> It's not hard.
>> I'm going to ask you this one. I'm sure
this is going to be easy, too, because
you keep talking about it. As we are
getting introduced to you and as our
audience is getting introduced to you,
and I'm sure they're already enjoying
this a great deal. What's your why?
>> My family. My family. But I have two
families. It's very important. Stacy,
Laney, and Luke are my family. They are
my family. I love them. unconditionally
in a way that a dad loves kids and a
husband loves a wife and I know love me
the same. But there's a football family
here too in these bu in these walls.
They're going to be loved
unconditionally football-wise
>> because everybody needs that love.
>> Yeah.
>> Everybody needs those relationships. And
I can't wait to build continue to build
my why with my own family, but start to
really build, which we already have,
this why and this love with this family
because then I know the playing hard,
playing fast, and playing violent. When
you have a love for each other and a
connection to you, that bond's
unbreakable. It's it's proven. It is
proven. When you love each other and
know about each other, hard times and
good times, they can't mess with us.
They can't mess with us. And when we'll
enjoy celebrating together because we
are going to celebrate. We are going to
celebrate.
>> Coach, it was it is awesome to have you
here. It is great to finally meet you.
I've been
>> loving it from afar and the pressers and
stuff, but it's great having you in the
in the studio with us. Uh can't wait to
see what you do with this defense. Uh
welcome to Cleveland. I know you've been
here for a little bit for you and your
family. I think it's going to treat you
well. And
>> you guys got to be the mayor of
Cleveland.
>> There's no doubt.
>> So cool to have you, man.
>> We want our defense to play great and
help us win a championship.
>> Absolutely. You said it, buddy. That's
your new defensive coordinator, Mike
Rutenberg. joined us uh here in studio.